Guide to the Andover Newton Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Individuals M-Z, Series II
  - Morrow, Honoré Willsie
    - Essays on Splendor of God by Louise Hobson, Mrs. Alexander Pausley, Alice Purington, No date (Box 103, Folder 5)
  - Morton, Margaret M.
    Morton, born in 1898, appears to have been involved in Christian education and church events.
    - Bibliography on "Prayer and the Devotional Life", ca. 1966 (Box 104, Folder 1)
    - Poems, choral readings, recitations, plays, etc. prepared by Morton for church worship services, No date (Box 104, Folder 2-13)
  - Niijima, Jó [Neesima]
    Nijiima Jó, better known by his English name Joseph Hardy Neesima, was a Japanese missionary and educator who founded Doshisha University and Doshisha Women's College of Liberal Arts. He was born in Tokyo on February 12, 1843, arrived in the U.S. in 1865, and graduated from Amherst College in 1870. He completed a Special Course at Andover Theological Seminary and was ordained at Mt. Vernon Church (Congregational) in Boston in 1874. From 1874 until his death in 1890 Niijima was a corresponding member of American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions,Japan Mission, Kyoto.
    - Letters written by Niijima to Mary Hidden, with whom he resided while a student at Amherst College, primarily from Amherst, MA, 1867-1870 (Box 105, Folder 1-4)
      A complete listing of letters is available in the first folder.
    - Letters to Mary Hidden following Niijima's graduation from Amherst, including written from Boston, Andover, London, Wiesbaden, New York, San Francisco, Kyoto; and one letter from Mary Hidden to Niijima, 1871-1874 (Box 105, Folder 5-7)
    - Letters to Mary Hidden, primarily from Japan; copy of letter to Mrs. Hardy, 1875-1885 (Box 105, Folder 8-9)
    - Letters of Mary Hidden not related to Niijima (received with collection), 1868-1877 (Box 105, Folder 10)
  - Nowlan, Ivan S.
    Nowlan was born in Nova Scotia, attended Acadia College, and graduated from the University of Chicago Divinity School in 1916. He served as General Secretary of the Massachusetts Sunday School Association.
    - Typescript writings and notes on the history of the Massachusetts Sunday School Association and the Massachusetts Council of Religious Education, and other aspects of religious education in Massachusetts, from late 1800s through mid 1930s (Box 106, Folder 1-3)
    - Minutes of the Joint Committee of the Massachusetts Council of Religious Education and the Massachusetts Sunday School Association, 1918-1919 (Box 106, Folder 4)
    - Financial documents related to the Massachusetts Sunday School Association, 1919-1924 (Box 106, Folder 5)
    - Annual convention reports, historical pamphlet, and journal of Massachusetts Sunday School Association, 1892-1904 (Box 106, Folder 6)
    - Published material regarding religious education programs in Massachusetts, 1917-1930 (Box 106, Folder 7)
  - Noyes, Charles Lothrop
    Noyes was born in Ceylon on September 11, 1851, the son of missionaries serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. He graduated from Yale University in 1875 and from Andover Theological Seminary ini 1880. He was ordained in 1881 and served the Winter Hill Congregational Church in Somerville, MA and the Broadway Winter Hill Church. Noyes was a Trustee of Andover Theological Seminary from 1907 to 1923 and was Chairman of the Executive Committee. He died on August 8, 1932.
    - Correspondence and documents related to Noyes' service on the Board of Trustees of Andover Theological Seminary, 1908-1922, 1927 (Box 107, Folder 1-8)
    - Program and letter related to naming of Charles Lothrop Noyes Hall at Andover Newton Theological School, 1943 (Box 107, Folder 9)
  - Page, Frederick Harlan
    Page was born on December 18, 1860 in Haverhill, MA. He worked as a journalist and editor in the Boston area prior to his graduation from Andover Theological Seminary in 1893. He was ordained as a Congregational minister and served churches in Boston, Lawrence, and Waltham, MA. Page was a Trustee of Andover Theological Seminary from 1909-1915 and 1919-1947. He served as President of the Massachusetts Missionary Society from 1925-1927 and President of the Massachusetts Congregational Christian Conference and Missionary Society from 1927-1934. He died in Waltham, MA on November 29, 1951.
    - Fragments of original diary, 1889-1942 (Box 108, Folder 1)
      According to a paper by Vaughan Dabney, "Selections from the Diaries of Frederick Harlan Page," fifty-two diary volumes were given to Andover Newton Theological School by Page in the early 1950s. Dabney was asked to read through the volumes, select entries for "their interest for the Seminary friends of Dr. Page," and destroy the volumes. This folder contains a few original holograph pages from the diary.
    - Typescript document: "Selections from the Diaries of Frederic Harlan Page, D.D. together with Service of Dedication of the Page Library and Addresses at the Funeral and Memorial Services also other Papers and Memorabilia" arranged by Vaughan Dabney, no date (Box 108, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: five letters, including from Page to Dabney (2), Page to A.S. Batchelder, and Owen Sanders to Page, 1893-1947 (Box 108, Folder 3)
    - Sermon notes, 1904-1911 (Box 108, Folder 4)
    - Addresses, including "Conduct of a Funeral Service" delivered before the Andover Association, 1899-1924 (Box 108, Folder 5)
    - Series of lectures on the Conduct of Public Worship Page delivered while a lecturer in Pastoral Theology at ATS (#1-21), 1900 (Box 108, Folder 6-15)
    - Lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary: George Harris/Christian Theology - volume 1, 1891 (Box 108, Folder 16)
    - Lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary: George Harris/Christian Theology - volume 2, 1891 (Box 109, Folder 1)
    - Lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary: Edward Hincks / Life of Christ, 1892-1893 (Box 109, Folder 2)
    - Lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary: George F. Moore / Introduction to the Study of the Old Testament, 1892-1893 (Box 109, Folder 3)
    - Lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary: George F. Moore / Old Testament Biblical Theology, 1891-1892 (Box 110, Folder 1)
    - Lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary: George F. Moore / Notes on Hebrew. 2 volumes, 1891 (Box 110, Folder 2)
    - Lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary: William H. Ryder / Lectures in Greek Exegesis (Gospel of Matthew), 1891-1892 (Box 110, Folder 3)
    - Lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary: Egbert C. Smyth / History of Christian Doctrine, 1892-1893 (Box 111, Folder 1)
    - Lectures from Andover Theological Seminary: [John Phelps] Taylor / Lectures on Biblical History, 1891 (Box 111, Folder 2)
    - Lectures from Andover Theological Seminary: William J. Tucker / Homiletics, 1892-1893 (Box 111, Folder 3)
    - Lectures from Andover Theological Seminary: William J. Tucker / Lectures in Social Economics, 1891-1892 (Box 112, Folder 1)
    - Lecture notes from Harvard Divinity School Summer School of Theology, 1904 (Box 112, Folder 2-7)
    - Miscellaneous notebooks: "Apostle's Creed" (1895); "Greek notes and exercises" (1891); "Memoranda"(notes on sermons in ATS chapel and area churches, 1891-1893); [Sermon illustration resources]; Theology of the New England Pulpit, 1891-1895 (Box 112, Folder 8)
    - Sermon evaluations while student at ATS, 1892-1893 (Box 112, Folder 9)
  - Pearson, Eliphalet
    Pearson was born June 11, 1752 in Newbury, Massachusetts. After graduation from Harvard College in 1773 he stayed in Cambridge for further study and was later licensed to preach. Pearson was the first principal of Phillips Academy when it opened in 1778 and served as President of its Board of Trustees. In 1786 he returned to Cambridge to accept the Hancock Professorship of Hebrew and Oriental Languages at Harvard and was named Acting President in 1804. In 1806 Pearson broke all ties with Harvard due to disagreement with the Unitarian sympathies of newly appointed professor Henry Ware. He returned to Andover and was instrumental in the establishment of Andover Theological Seminary. He served as Associate Professor of Sacred Literature at ATS for one year and continued as President of the Board of Trustees until 1821. He died September 12, 1826.
    - Letter from E. Wigglesworth to Pearson, from Cambridge, 1776 (Box 113, Folder 1)
    - Sermons, 1776-1815, no date (Box 113, Folder 2-12)
    - Lectures on language, #1-27, 1786-1788 (Box 113, Folder 13-27)
    - Lectures on language, #32-46, 1788-1798 (Box 114, Folder 1-7)
    - "A Chaldee Grammar founded on the writings of Daniel and Ezra", No date (Box 114, Folder 8)
    - "A compendious Syriac Grammar", 1773 (Box 114, Folder 9)
    - "Grammatical Extracts and References", 1786 (Box 114, Folder 10)
    - "A Hebrew grammar - Section I, Of letters", No date (Box 114, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts on language, including lists of words, No date (Box 114, Folder 12-15)
    - Notes on readings, No date (Box 114, Folder 16)
    - Manuscript items related to Harvard College, including examination schedules, list of important dates, 1792-1805, no date (Box 114, Folder 17)
    - Collected material: charters of Dartmouth College (1754) and North Kingston Academy (1800), 1792-1805 (Box 114, Folder 18)
    - Letter from Margaret B. Pearson to Samuel Farrar, 1754 (Box 114, Folder 19)
  - Peck, George Willis
    Peck was born in Ipswich, Queensland, Australia on March 4, 1931. He received B.A. and M.A. degrees from the University of Queensland and a B.D. degree from Melbourne College of Divinity. Peck was appointed missionary to India by the Australian Baptist Foreign Mission Society and his services were loaned to the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society from 1958 to 1963. He came to the U.S. on study leave in 1963 to pursue doctoral studies at Harvard University.
    Peck was appointed Dean of Andover Newton Theological School in 1966 and taught courses in theology, New Testament, Greek, and missiology in his dual role as Judson Professor of Christian Theology and International Mission. He was appointed President of Andover Newton in 1983. Peck and his wife Mary had just returned from sabbatical leave in Czechoslovakia when he died unexpectedly on January 17, 1990.
    - Sermons, 1956-1977, no date (Box 115, Folder 1-19)
      For a listing of sermon titles, see inventory of the collection in the first folder of Box 115.
    - Sermons, 1978-1989 (Box 116, Folder 1-12)
    - Addresses, 1965-1989, no date (Box 117, Folder 1-15)
      For incomplete listing of address titles, see inventory of the collection in first folder of box 115.
    - Addresses, writings, notes on Baptists, 1970s-1980s (Box 118, Folder 1-3)
    - Addresses, writings, and notes on church growth and evangelism, 1970s-1980s (Box 118, Folder 4-5)
    - Talks and notes related to Bible Lands tour, 1985 (Box 118, Folder 6)
    - Memorials and eulogies, 1979-1987 (Box 118, Folder 7)
    - Writings: prayers, 1971-1979 (Box 118, Folder 8)
    - Writings: unpublished manuscripts and drafts for published material, 1972-1989, no date (Box 118, Folder 9-10)
    - Writings: typescript book reviews, 1973-1987, no date (Box 118, Folder 11)
    - Course-related material, syllabi (Box 118, Folder 12-20)
    - Collected material: papers and essays related to Baptists (Box 119, Folder 1)
    - Collected material: selected typescript writings and sermons by Andover Newton Theological School faculty, including James Luther Adams, M. B. Handspicker, Eleanor McLaughlin (Box 119, Folder 2)
    - Personal correspondence, 1965-1979 (Box 119, Folder 3-5)
    - Personal correspondence during sabbatical, 1989 (Box 119, Folder 6)
    - Photographs and memorabilia (Box 119, Folder 7)
  - Pendleton, Othniel A.
    Pendleton was born August 22, 1911 in Washington, District of Columbia. He graduated from Union College in 1933, Eastern Baptist Theological Seminary in 1936, and received his Ph.D. from the University of Pennsylvania in 1945. Ordained as a Baptist minister, Pendleton was a fund-raiser and campaign director for churches and councils of churches throughout the country. He was a lecturer at Andover Newton Theological School in 1958.
    - Notebook prepared by Pendleton on "Some Financial Results Achieved through the Sector Project of the American Baptist Convention 1951-1953" (Box 120, Folder 1)
    - Notebook related to Every Member Canvass initiated by the Department of Missionary Co-operation of the Massachusetts Baptist Convention, 1951 (Box 120, Folder 2)
    - Notebook related to Rhode Island United Church Canvass, 1952 (Box 120, Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook related to the Springfield Interdenominational Sector Project and United Church Canvass, 1953 (Box 120, Folder 4)
    - Notebook related to Newton Council of Churches United Canvass, 1954 (Box 120, Folder 5)
    - Notebook relating to Washington Council of Churches (Seattle) fundraising campaign, 1956 (Box 120, Folder 6)
    - Notebook related to First Baptist Church in Newton, MA fundraising campaign, 1961-1964 (Box 120, Folder 7)
    - Notebook related to Woodstock, CT Congregational Church fundraising campaign, 1964 (Box 120, Folder 8)
  - Pepper, George Dana Boardman
    Pepper was born February 5, 1833 in Ware, Massachusetts. He attended Amherst College and graduated from the Newton Theological Institution in 1860. He served a Baptist church in Waterville, Maine until 1865 when he was called to the chair of Church History at NTI. In 1867 he accepted the chair of Systematic Theology at the Crozer Theological Seminary, where he remained for 15 years. Pepper served as President of Colby College from 1882 to 1889. He died on January 30, 1913.
    - Notes taken on the subjects Christian Ethics, Theology, and Christian Ministry while a student at Newton Theological Institution, ca. 1857-1860 (Box 121, Folder 1)
    - Lectures and essays from years teaching, including at Newton Theological Institution, ca. 1865-1870s (Box 121, Folder 2-6)
  - Phillips, Samuel
    Phillips was born February 17, 1690 in Salem, Massachusetts. He graduated from Harvard College in 1708. In 1711 he was ordained as a Congregational minister and served South Church, Andover, MA from 1711 to 1771. He died in Andover in 1771.
    - Sermons: Book 2, 1716-1750 (Box 122, Folder 1-4)
      The sermons are arranged primarily according to a scheme developed by Phillips: Books 2-12. The order within the books is chronological, although there are some exceptions to the numerical sequence imposed by Phillips. For a full list of scriptural texts for the sermons, see the first folder in Box 122.
      Microfilm copy available.
    - Sermons: Book 3, Book 4 (pp. 1-264), 1718-1750 (Box 123, Folder 1-4)
    - Sermons: Book 4 (pp. 265-824), Book 5, 1720-1770 (Box 124, Folder 1-4)
    - Sermons: Books 7-11, 1743-1776 (Box 125, Folder 1-5)
    - Sermons: Book 12, additional sermons and notes, 1747-1766, no date (Box 126, Folder 1-4)
  - Plumb, Albert Hale, Jr.
    Hale was born December 8, 1863 in Chelsea, Massachusetts. He graduated from Amherst College in 1891 and received theological training at Hartford Seminary. After some years of teaching, he was ordained in 1899 and served Congregational churches, including in Peru, Vermont. He died in 1961.
    - Sermons, 1898-1899 (Box 127, Folder 1-20)
      The dates noted are for when the sermon was first delivered. Each sermon is annotated with the places and dates where it was delivered. A list of sermon titles and texts is available in the first folder of box 127.
    - Sermons, 1899-1904 (Box 128, Folder 1-19)
    - Sermons, 1905-1914 (Box 129, Folder 1-21)
    - Sermons, 1915-1916 (Box 130, Folder 1-21)
    - Sermons, 1916-1927, no date (Box 131, Folder 1-20)
    - Collected material, 1928-1929, no date (Box 131, Folder 21)
  - Plumb, Albert Hale, Sr.
    Hale, the father of Albert Hale Plumb Jr., was born in Gowanda, New York on August 23, 1829. He graduated from Brown University in 1855 and from Andover Theological Seminary in 1858. Ordained as a Congregational minister, he served First Church in Chelsea, MA and the Walnut Avenue Congregational Church in Boston.
    - Correspondence, including to Board of Visitors of Andover Theological Seminary regarding theological beliefs of a professor, 1883, 1897 (Box 132, Folder 1)
    - Published sermons and articles, including regarding missions, Sabbath observance, gambling, 1890-1905, no date (Box 132, Folder 2)
    - Published tracts, written for New England Sabbath Protective League: "Sunday Golf", "Importance and Necessity of our Work"; poem about Santa Claus; statements to Walnut Avenue Congregational Church members, 1905-1907, no date (Box 132, Folder 3)
    - Letters to the editor and newspaper accounts of sermons by Plumb, including regarding Andover Creed, Sunday golf, comics, theology, 1890-1904, no date (Box 132, Folder 4)
    - Unpublished sermons and articles, including regarding missions, temperance, Sabbath observance, higher criticism, theology, 1894-1905, no date (Box 132, Folder 5-9)
    - Collected material, including issues of Daily Bible, tracts, pamphlets, 1866-1904, no date (Box 132, Folder 10-11)
  - Price, Hampton Eugene
    Price was born in Blythewood, South Carolina on June 9, 1904. He graduated from Furman University in 1924 and received the B.D. degree from Newton Theological Institution in 1936, as well as the S.T.M. degree (1971) and D.Min. degree (1973) from Andover Newton Theological School. Price served the following churches: Hill Memorial Baptist Church, Boston, MA (1936-1942); The Federated Church, Ashland, MA (1942-1949); Clearfield Community Church, Clearfield, UT (1949-1956); Woodlawn Baptist Church, Chicago, IL (1956-1962). In April 1962, he became Executive Director of Gould Farm in Monterey, MA, a residential therapeutic community for adults with mental illness, and remained there until his retirement in 1972. He then served as pastor at Dunstable Congregational Church, MA, until 1979 before returning to South Carolina. He died on June 3, 1991.
    - Sermons, 1936-1984 (Box 133, Folder 1-7)
      The collection is comprised of a selection of sermons representing the life work of Price. Other sermons remain with the family. The arrangement is chronological by the first date each sermon was preached. In almost all cases there are several dates for each sermon. A listing of sermon titles and texts is available in the first folder.
  - Rhees, Rush
    Rhees was born February 8, 1860 in Chicago. He graduated from Amherst College in 1883 and from Hartford Theological Seminary in 1888. Ordained as a Baptist minister, he served a church in Portsmouth, NH from 1888-1892 before becoming professor of Biblical Interpretation, New Testament at Newton Theological Institution from 1892 to 1900. He then taught Biblical Literature at the University of Rochester from 1900 to 1921 and was President of the university from 1900 to 1935. He died on January 5, 1939 in Rochester.
    - The Life of Paul: Notes of Lectures to the Junior Class in the Newton Theological Institution (Privately printed, 1897) (Box 134, Folder 1)
    - Draft of "The Life of Paul" (fragmentary)., No date (Box 134, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous lecture notes on the life of Paul, No date (Box 134, Folder 3-8)
  - Sanderson, Ross Warren
    Sanderson was born in 1884. He graduated from Oberlin College in 1905 and Oberlin Theological Seminary in 1908. He was ordained as a Congregational minister in 1908 and served churches, including in Lakewood, Ohio. He served as Executive Secretary for Councils of Churches in Wichita, Kansas (1920-1929), Maryland-Delaware (1932-1937), and Buffalo-Erie County (1937-1942). During World War II he served as a representative for the National Church Relations of the American Red Cross. From 1944 to 1952 he was Director of Field Research, Bureau of Home Missons, United Church of Christ. Sanderson was the author of The Church Serves the Changing City (1955), Church Cooperation in the United States (1960), B.F. Lamb, Ecumenical Pioneer (1964).
    - Autobiography,"Fallible Churchman" - " Family Archives" chapters 1-15, circa 1974 (Box 135, Folder 1-3)
    - Autobiography, "Fallible Churchman" - "Ecumenical Chronicle" pp. 1-1969 (Box 135, Folder 4-6, Box 136, Folder 1-5, Box 137, Box 138, Folder 1-6, Box 139, Folder 1-7)
    - Documentation related to Association of Council Secretaries and its predecessors, 1931-1967 (Box 140, Folder 1-6)
      The Association of Council Secretaries (ACS)was formed in 1940 by the merger of the Association of Executive Secretaries (AES), inaugurated by the Field Department of the Federal Council of Churches, and the Employed Council Officers Association (ECOA), sponsored by the International Council of Religious Education.
  - Schauffler, William Gottlieb
    Schauffler was born August 22, 1798 in Stuttgart, Germany. After serving as an independent missionary in Turkey, he made his way to the United States in 1826 and entered Andover Theological Seminary. He was graduated in 1830, was ordained on November 14, 1831, and returned to Turkey under the auspices of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. He served in Turkey for 44 years and translated the Bible into Turkish. Schauffler died in New York on January 27, 1883.
    - Manuscript of translation of Bible into Turkish: Old Testament, 2 Kings 3:24 to end of Malachi, No date (Box 141, Folder 1-4)
  - Smith, Hezekiah
    Smith was born April 21, 1737 in Long Island, New York. He graduated from Princeton University in 1762 and received an A.M. degree from Princeton in 1765. Smith was ordained as a Baptist minister in 1763 and served the First Baptist Church, Haverhill, MA from 1765 to until his death in 1805. He was a Chaplain in the Continental Army 1776 to 1780.
    - Four memorandum books, 1757 -1775 (Box 142, Folder 1-4)
      1758 book consists of Smith's recording of "The Laws and Customs of the College of New Jersey"; other books include notes regarding pastoral work.
    - Two essays: "The Antinomian errors considered" and untitled, No date (Box 142, Folder 5)
    - Two addresses: delivered at ordinations of Thomas Gair and Thomas Baldwin, 1788, 1790 (Box 142, Folder 6)
    - Sermons, 1763-1804, no date (Box 142, Folder 7-10, Box 143, Folder 1-2)
      For a full listing of dates and texts of sermons, see folder 7.
    - Last Will and Testament of Hezekiah Smith, 1802 (Box 143, Folder 3)
    - Collected material: Printed address of Congregational ministers in Massachusetts, 1799 (Box 143, Folder 4)
  - Smith, Samuel Francis
    Smith was born in Boston on October 21, 1808. He graduated from Harvard in 1829 and received a certificate from Andover Theological Seminary in 1832. Ordained as a Baptist minister in 1834, he served First Baptist Church, Watervi11e, Maine and as Professor of Modern Languages, Colby College from 1834 to 1842, minister at First Baptist Church, Newton, Massachusetts from 1842-1854, and pulpit supply at Second Baptist Church, Newton Upper Falls, Massachusetts from 1856 to 1865. He was editor of the Baptist Missionary Magazine (1832-1833)and the Christian Review (1842-1848), and Editorial Secretary for the American Baptist Missionary Union from 1848-1863. Smith is best known for having written the lyrics to the song "America" also known as "My Country, 'Tis of Thee." He died in Boston on November 16, 1895.
    For a more detailed listing of the collection, see the inventory in Box 144, Folder 1.
    - Hymns (Box 144, Folder 1-6)
      The hymns by Smith are arranged alphabetically by title. They are primarily in manuscript format, with some printed versions.
    - Poems (Box 144, Folder 7-11)